Welcome to another edition
of JW Broadcasting.
JW Broadcastingにようこそ！
Here are this month’s highlights:
今月のハイライトでは
米国サンフランシスコの雑踏で行なう—
What is it like to engage
in the special metropolitan witnessing work
特別な公の証言を
体験してみましょう
in the bustling United States city
of San Francisco?
We’ll hear encouraging experiences
from brothers and sisters
異なった言語を話す人のいる
この区域で宣べ伝えている—
兄弟姉妹の経験を聞きましょう
who preach
in this diverse language field.
Can young ones
serve Jehovah successfully
若い人は 家族が
霊的な活動をやめても—
even if their family’s
spiritual activity stops?
エホバに仕えつづけられるでしょうか？
We’ll hear from a sister who tells
what kept her love for Jehovah growing
家族がショービジネスで忙しい中—
どのようにエホバへの愛を成長させたか—
throughout her family’s
busy show business career.
姉妹の経験を聞きましょう
“結婚に備える”シリーズでは—
In our Preparing for Marriage series,
we’ll learn how those who are dating
交際中の人が
生涯続く厳粛な約束をする前に—
can get to know
“the secret person of the heart”
どうすれば“心の中の秘められた人”を
知れるかを学びます
before making
a solemn lifelong commitment.
そして忠節という素晴らしい
特質についても考えます
And we’ll discuss
the beautiful quality of loyalty,
including an interview with a couple
また60年以上
エホバに忠節に仕えてきた—
who has served Jehovah loyally
for over 60 years.
ご夫婦のインタビューもあります
All this is ahead
on JW Broadcasting for August 2016.
それでは2016年8月の
JW Broadcastingです
This month’s theme is taken
from David’s poetic song to Jehovah
今月のテーマは詩編 18:25の—
エホバに対するダビデの歌から
とられています
at Psalm 18:25, which states:
“忠節な者にはあなたは
忠節をもって行動する“とあります
“With someone loyal you act in loyalty.”
The Hebrew term “act in loyalty”
“忠節をもって行動する”という
ヘブライ語は神の忠節な愛を連想させ—
reminds us
of God’s loyal love
—that is love motivated
by commitment,
それは誓約 忠誠 忠節 また深い愛着
によって動機づけられる愛のことです
integrity, loyalty,
and deep attachment.
So loyalty is more
than just a feeling;
ですから忠節は単なる感情ではなく
行動が伴い 愛に根ざしています
it is active;
it’s rooted in love.
How comforting it is
to know that Jehovah
エホバが忠節な者に—
lovingly attaches himself
to those who are loyal to him!
愛を込めて密着してくださるのを
知るのは慰めです
But what motivated David
to write the words
しかしダビデはなぜ
詩編 18:25を書いたのですか？
at Psalm 18:25?
The superscription reveals
that it was composed
表題を見るとこの詩編は
“エホバが敵のたなごころより—”
after “Jehovah rescued him
from the hand of all his enemies
“またサウルの手より
救い出してくださった”後に書かれました
and from the hand of Saul.”
Think of the great joy
and relief he must have felt
エホバの忠節な愛と強力な救いを
経験したダビデが感じた—
after experiencing firsthand
Jehovah’s loyal love
喜びと安ど感について
考えてみてください
and mighty saving acts.
However, throughout his life,
しかしダビデは生涯にわたりー
David experienced
disloyalty at its worst:
最悪ともいえる不忠節な仕打ちを
経験しました
from his king, Saul;
from his wife Michal;
それは王サウル 妻ミカル
信頼した助言者アヒトフェルー
from his trusted counselor Ahithophel;
and from his son Absalom.
息子アブサロムからのものです
最も信頼し愛した者たちの裏切りにより
ダビデの心は深く傷つきました
He felt the deep hurt of betrayal
by those he trusted and loved most.
Loyalty is a choice.
忠節は選べます
What do we find when we look back
at David’s life?
ダビデの生涯を振り返ると
何が分かりますか？
David chose to stay loyal to God.
ダビデは神への忠節を選びました
謙遜な羊飼いの少年の時から—
From a humble shepherd boy
caring for his sheep
国民を世話する
勇敢な王となるまでずっと—
to a valiant king
caring for the nation,
ダビデはエホバの心にかなう
忠節な者であることを示しました
he proved
to be someone loyal,
a man agreeable
to Jehovah’s heart.
But it can be a real test
to maintain loyalty to God
しかし不公平に直面すると—
神に忠節を保つことは
難しくなるものです
when we face injustices.
Imagine the desperate situation
that David and his mighty warriors
ダビデと勇敢な部下たちが
味わった—
切迫した状況を想像してください
experienced when they
were fugitives,
forced to hide in the wilderness,
often low on provisions.
荒野に隠れ 蓄えもたびたび底を
尽くほどでした
They saw firsthand
King Saul’s jealous rage.
嫉妬にかられたサウル王の怒りに
直面しました
しかしサウルの命を奪うよう
部下たちに促されたとき—
But what choice did David make
when urged by his men
to seize the opportunity
to take Saul’s life?
ダビデはどんな選択をしましたか？
Notice what David told his men
サムエル第一 24:6で—
ダビデが何と述べたか
注目してください
at 1 Samuel 24:6:
“わたしが彼に向って手を出して—”
“It is unthinkable
from Jehovah’s standpoint
“わたしの主に
エホバの油そそがれた者に—”
“that I should do
such a thing to my lord,
“このような事をするなど
わたしには エホバの見地からして—”
“the anointed of Jehovah,
by lifting my hand against him,
“考えられないことだ”
for he is the anointed of Jehovah.”
“彼はエホバの油そそがれた者なのだ”
David knew that if he remained loyal,
ダビデは自分が忠節であれば
エホバも自分に忠節であり—
Jehovah would remain loyal to him
忠節な愛を示してくださることを
知っていました
—He would show him loyal love.
He humbly put aside
his personal feelings
ダビデは個人的な感情を
脇において—
and viewed matters
from Jehovah’s perspective.
エホバの見地から
物事を見るようにしました
He chose to wait patiently
for Jehovah to “act in loyalty.”
”忠節をもって行動”してくださるのを
辛抱強く待ちました
まもなく聖書の予告どおり—
We’ll soon be facing
life-changing events foretold in the Bible
エホバとその組織への
忠節の試みとなる—
that will test our loyalty
to Jehovah and his organization.
人生を一変させるほどの
出来事に直面します
So now is the time
to strengthen our loyalty!
今こそ忠節を強化するときです
As we do, we can be sure
that Jehovah knows our circumstances
そうするなら エホバがわたしたちの
直面する不公正な状況をご存じであり—
—perhaps injustices
we have experienced—
わたしたちの忠節な奉仕に
報いてくださることを確信できます
and will reward our loyal service.
So ask yourself, ‘What loyal actions
こう自問しましょう
“忠節のどんな行ないに基づいて—”
will motivate Jehovah to be loyal to me?’
“エホバはわたしに忠節を
示してくださるだろうか？”
Let’s consider three areas.
3つ考えてみましょう
First, we can be loyal
to Jehovah by defending him.
第一に エホバを擁護することによって
忠節を示せます
But Jehovah is
the Sovereign of the universe.
でもエホバは宇宙の主権者です
How can we come to his defense?
どのように擁護できるでしょうか？
We can learn how
from the fine example of Elihu!
エリフの立派な模範から学べます
In the book of Job,
Elihu listened patiently as Job
エリフはヨブと
3人の偽りの慰め手が語る時—
and his three false comforters spoke.
辛抱強く耳を傾けました
Notice Elihu’s reaction
エリフの反応に注目してください
at Job 32:2, 3:
ヨブ 32:2，3
“His anger blazed against Job
“ヨブに対して彼の怒りが燃え盛った”
“ヨブが神よりも自分の魂を
義と宣したことに対してであった”
“for trying to prove himself
right rather than God.
“He was also very angry
with Job’s three companions
“また その三人の友に対しても—”
“彼の怒りは燃え盛った”
“because they could not find an answer
“これは彼らが答えを見いださずー”
but had declared God wicked.”
“かえって神を邪悪な者と
したからである”
A fire of righteous indignation
was burning inside young Elihu.
義憤の火が
若いエリフの中で燃えたのです
ヨブ 36:2, 3でエリフは
エホバを忠節に擁護してこう語りました
In Job 36:2, 3,
he loyally comes
to Jehovah’s defense saying:
“わたしのことを辛抱するように”
“Be patient with me
a little longer while I explain,
“わたしはあなたに告げ知らせよう”
“まだ 神のために
言うべき言葉があるということを”
“for I still have words
to speak on God’s behalf.
“I will speak comprehensively
about what I know,
“わたしは遠くから
わたしの知識を携えて来てー”
“わたしを形作った方に
義を帰することにする”
and I will ascribe
righteousness to my Maker.”
Elihu courageously proved loyal
エリフは神を賛美し
擁護することによって—
by praising,
and, yes, defending God.
勇気をもって忠節を示しました
Why do we need to come
to Jehovah’s defense today?
今日 なぜわたしたちも
エホバを擁護すべきですか?
Because our loving heavenly Father
is blasphemed in so many ways.
愛ある天の父がさまざまな
非難を受けているからです
False religions claim
that he’s part of a Trinity
神は三位一体の一部で—
地獄の火で人々を永遠に
苦しめていると教えられています
and that he torments people
eternally in burning hell.
Others say that he
does not exist or if he does,
神はいないとか—
いたとしてもわたしたちのことなど
気にかけていないというのです
he doesn’t really care about us.
We know that such lies
come from Satan the Devil.
そのようなうそは
サタン悪魔から出ています
We demonstrate our loyalty
エホバを擁護するために語り
サタンのうそを証明することによって—
by speaking in defense of Jehovah,
わたしたちの忠節を示しましょう
thereby proving
Satan the liar that he is.
全能の神が実在していることを
大胆かつ熱心に宣明し—
We boldly and zealously proclaim
that he does exist
as the almighty God;
賢明で義にかない愛のあるその方が
まもなく悪を終わらせ—
and that he is
wise, just, and loving,
and that he will soon
bring an end to all evil
忠節な者に永遠の命を
与えることを知らせるのです
and reward his loyal ones
with eternal life.
Jehovah could make
the stones cry out in defense,
エホバは石に叫ばせることも
できますが—
yet he honors his loyal Witnesses
—you and me—
この特権をわたしたちに与えて
忠節な者に誉れを与えておられます
with this fine privilege.
Second, we can be loyal
to Jehovah by being loyal
第二に “忠実で思慮深い奴隷”である—
統治体に忠節を示すことで
エホバに忠節を示せます
to “the faithful and discreet slave,”
the Governing Body.
Jehovah and Jesus are using
“the faithful and discreet slave”
エホバとイエスは霊的な食物を与えるために
この“奴隷”を用いています
to feed us spiritually,
so we owe our loyalty to that slave.
ですからその奴隷に忠節を示すべきです
But some may say,
でも“統治体も不完全な人間から
成っている”と言うかもしれません
‘Isn’t the Governing Body
made up of imperfect men?’
Yes, it is.
その通りです
The last perfect person to walk
the earth was Jesus himself.
地上で完全な生き方をしたのは
イエスだけです
There is no perfect person
or organization on the globe.
地球上には完全な人や組織は
存在しません
長年忠実だった兄弟は
よくこう言いました—
But as a long-time faithful brother
used to say,
“This is the best imperfect organization
on earth.”
“これは地上で最善の不完全な組織です”
Jesus didn’t say
the slave would be infallible.
奴隷は間違いをしないと
イエスは言いませんでした
He said it would be
faithful and discreet.
忠実で思慮深いと言われたのです
The way we listen to
and obey the faithful slave
忠実な奴隷にどのように聞き
また従うかは—
has a direct bearing on the strength
of our friendship with God.
神との友情の強さに
直接影響を与えます
In fact, it means our very life.
実際 それは命を左右します
But what if the Governing Body
では統治体がわたしたちの好まない
霊的食物を提供したならどうですか？
serves some spiritual food
that is not to our liking?
Or what if we do not fully understand
またある信条の説明がよく理解できず
同意できない場合はどうですか？
or agree with a clarification of a belief?
On one occasion, Jesus’ followers,
including the apostle Peter,
ある時 ペテロを含む
イエスの弟子たちは—
新しい教えを示されました
were confronted
with a new teaching.
皆の反応はどうでしたか？
How did most react?
ヨハネ 6:60をご覧ください
Notice John 6:60, it states:
“弟子のうち大勢の者は
これを聞いた際にー”
“When they heard this,
many of his disciples said:
“この話はひどい”
‘This speech is shocking;
who can listen to it?’”
“だれがこれをきいていられようかと言った”
The result?
どうなりましたか？
Continuing in verse 66:
66節
“Because of this,
many of his disciples
“このために 弟子のうち多くの者が
後ろのものに戻って行きー”
went off to the things behind
and would no longer walk with him.”
“もはや彼と共に歩もうとはしなかった”
But how did Peter respond
when Jesus asked them,
しかし“あなたもつまずきましたか？”
とのイエスの問いに—
‘Are you too stumbled?’
ペテロはどう反応しましたか？
At John 6:68, we read:
ヨハネ 6:68
“Simon Peter answered him:
“シモン・ペテロが彼に答えた”
‘Lord, whom shall we go away to?
“主よ わたしたちは誰のところに
行けばよいというのでしょう”
You have sayings of everlasting life.’”
“あなたこそ永遠の命のことばを
持っておられます”
What loyalty!
素晴らしい忠節です
Peter’s loyalty
was based on solid evidence
ペテロの忠節はイエスがメシアであるとの
確かな証拠に基づいていました
that Jesus was the Messiah.
His loyalty
was evidence of his faith.
その忠節は信仰の証拠でした
That is the kind of loyalty
we want to imitate today.
それこそわたしたちが
今日見倣いたい忠節です
There are times we must wait on
Jehovah to clarify matters.
エホバが物事を明確にされるのを
待つ必要もあります
In the meantime,
may we prove ourselves loyal like Peter
その間 ペテロのような忠節を
示せますように
そして主イエスの足跡に
しっかりと従った—
and follow closely
the lead of the faithful slave,
who closely follow
in the footsteps of their Master, Jesus.
忠実な奴隷の指導にしっかりと
付き従って行けますように
At times, though, we receive
counsel that touches us personally.
時々 個人的に必要な助言を
受けることがあります
For instance, on JW Broadcasting
we’ve received loving reminders
例えば
JW Broadcastingでは—
統治体の成員からの愛ある諭しが
与えられてきました
from members of the Governing Body
to be forgiving,
人を許すこと 貴重なものをもって
エホバを敬うこと—
to honor Jehovah
with our valuable things,
and to remain spiritually alert.
霊的に目覚めた状態を保つこと
などについてです
Through The Watchtower
and at Christian meetings,
「ものみの塔」誌や集会では—
we’re reminded to be careful
about our dress and grooming,
服装や身づくろいに気を付けること
良い仲間と健全な娯楽を選択すること—
to choose good associates
and wholesome entertainment,
また道徳的に清くあることなどについて
教えられました
and to remain morally clean.
Are we quick to respond
and make needed adjustments
すぐに当てはめ
必要な調整を図りますか？
or do we find ourselves wanting
to defend our personal rights?
それとも自分の権利を
主張しますか?
使徒パウロは神権的な指示に対する
忠節を試みられたことがありました
A situation
in the apostle Paul’s life
tested his loyalty
to theocratic direction.
It’s found in Acts chapter 21.
使徒21章にある記録です
パウロは宣教旅行から戻り
西暦56年 エルサレムに到着しました
As you recall,
Paul arrived in Jerusalem in 56 C.E.
after a very successful missionary tour.
“神が諸国民の間で行なわれた
事柄について” 詳しく話したときの—
You can imagine his excitement
as he related in detail
“the things God did among
the nations through his ministry.”
パウロの喜びを想像できるでしょう
After hearing
Paul’s extraordinary account,
パウロの驚くべき経験について
聞いたのち—
the older men revealed to Paul
年長者たちはパウロ個人が関係している
ユダヤにおける問題を明らかにしました
a problem in Judea
that involved him personally.
Read what they said
at Acts 21:21:
使徒 21:21の記録を
読んでみましょう
“しかし 彼ら［ユダヤ人の信者たち］は
あなたについてー”
“But they [the Jewish believers]
have heard it rumored about you
“that you have been teaching
all the Jews
“あなたが諸国民の中にいる
すべてのユダヤ人に対してー”
“among the nations
an apostasy from Moses,
“モーセからの背教を説き
子供に割礼を施すこともー”
“telling them
not to circumcise their children
“厳粛な習慣にしたがって
歩むこともしないように告げているー”
or to follow the customary practices.”
“とのうわさを聞いています”
Well, perhaps Paul thought,
‘Me, an apostate?
パウロはおそらくこう思ったでしょう
“自分が？ 背教？”
‘Really?
How can they say such a thing?
“どうしてそんなことを言うのか?”
‘I just finished
my third missionary tour,
“3回目の宣教旅行を
終えましたが—”
and look how
Jehovah blessed the work!’
“エホバの祝福を見てください！”
Nevertheless, the older men
gave Paul very clear direction
しかし年長者たちは
使徒21:23, 24で—
at Acts 21:23, 24
おそらくパウロが予期していなかった
明確な指示を与えました
that he likely did not anticipate,
“わたしたちが告げる
このことをしてください”
and there it reads:
“わたしたちのところには
誓約を立てた四人の人がいます”
“So do what we tell you:
“We have four men who have put
themselves under a vow.
“この人たちを連れて行ってー”
“Take these men with you
and cleanse yourself
“一緒に儀式上の清めをしー”
“その費用の世話を見てー”
“ceremonially together with them
and take care of their expenses,
“彼らが頭をそってもらえるー”
“ようにしてやりなさい”
“so that they may have
their heads shaved.
“こうすればだれもがー”
“Then everyone will know
that there is nothing
“あなたについて聞かされているー”
“うわさには何の根拠もなくー”
“to the rumors
they were told about you,
“あなたが秩序正しく歩んでー”
but that you are walking orderly
and you are also keeping the Law.”
“自らも律法を守っていることをー”
“知るでしょう”
Was this the time
for Paul to question
パウロはその決定を
疑問視したり—
their decision
or demand his rights?
自分の権利を主張したり
すべきでしたか?
He could have reasoned:
パウロは —
“律法はイエスと共に
杭につけられたという—”
‘Didn’t you read my letter
to the Galatians,
‘where it says the Law was nailed
to the torture stake with Jesus?
“ガラテア人への手紙を
読まなかったのですか？”
‘I did nothing wrong!
“わたしは間違っていない—”
‘Why do I have to put on
this pretense
“少数の過敏な人のために
なぜうわべを繕う必要があるのか？”
just because a few
are overly sensitive?’
と言うこともできました
No.
しかし パウロは命の
危険にもかかわらず—
He humbly did
as they requested,
although it
nearly cost him his life.
求めに謙遜に応じました
Yes, it meant swallowing his pride,
パウロは言わばプライドを
飲み込みました
but Paul knew
there were bigger issues
自分の権利よりも大きな事が
関係していることを知っていたのです
involved than his personal rights.
He was considerate
of the consciences of others.
パウロは他の人の良心に配慮しました
But more importantly,
より重要なことはエホバと統治体に
忠節を示したということです
he showed his loyalty to Jehovah
and to the governing body.
Do we see
the bigger issue in our life?
これよりも重要な事柄が
ほかにあるでしょうか?
Let us be determined
to be humble,
パウロのように謙遜に 柔軟に
そして従順になるよう決意し—
flexible,
and obedient like Paul,
and thereby
prove ourselves faithful
“忠実で思慮深い奴隷”に
忠実であることを示していきましょう
to “the faithful and discreet slave.”
第三として 長老たちに忠節であるなら
エホバに忠節でいられます
Third, we can be loyal to Jehovah
by being loyal to the elders.
We’ve discussed loyalty to Jehovah himself
and to the faithful slave,
エホバと忠実な奴隷に
忠節を示すことについて考えましたが—
but what about direction
we receive
会衆の長老たちから受ける
指示についてはどうでしょうか？
from the elders
in our congregation?
We listen
to our elders give talks
わたしたちは毎週集会で
長老たちの話や注解を聞き—
and comments
at the meetings each week,
we work with them
in the ministry,
宣教で共に働き 交わります
and we associate
with them.
定期的に接する機会が増えると—
This regular contact
gives us more opportunities
長老たちの不完全さや欠点が
目に留まる機会も増えます
to see their imperfections
and flaws.
We could begin to focus
on their weaknesses,
彼らの弱点に注目し—
神の取り決めに対する信頼を
弱めてしまうことが生じ得ます
weakening our trust
in God’s arrangement.
For example, if you zoom in
例えば雑誌に載っている写真を
拡大してみると—
on any of our pictures
in our magazines,
all you’ll see are colored spots or pixels.
カラーの小さな点や画素が
見えるでしょう
でも遠くから見ると
きれいな写真や絵となります
But when you zoom out,
you see a beautiful photo or painting.
同様に長老たちを見るとき
不完全さを拡大しないでください
Similarly, when looking at our elders,
don’t zoom in on their imperfections
—the spots of ink—
小さな点ではなく
全体を見るようにしてください
rather, see the big picture.
Why, then, is it so important
熱心に働く愛ある牧者への忠節は
なぜそれほど重要ですか？
to strengthen our loyalty
to our hard-working, loving shepherds?
Because these “gifts in men”
それはこれら“人々の賜物”が
エホバの忠節な愛の表明であり—
are an expression
of Jehovah’s loyal love
as they loyally lead, feed,
エホバの貴重な羊を導き 養い
保護してくれるからです
and protect
his precious sheep.
大患難が近い今
わたしたちの救いは—
As the great tribulation nears,
our survival will depend
統治体の指示に従っている長老たちに
進んで従うことにかかっています
on our readiness
to respond to their direction,
as they follow
the Governing Body’s direction.
Our loyalty is not to men,
忠節は人にではなく
不完全ながらも忠節な人々による—
but to Jehovah’s arrangement
made up of imperfect,
but loyal men.
エホバの取り決めに対するものです
That is a lesson
that Korah, Dathan,
それはコラ ダタン アビラムが
学ぶのを拒んだ教訓です
and Abiram refused to learn.
In this clip from the video
Respect Jehovah’s Authority,
民数記16章を扱った
「エホバの権威に敬意を払う」という—
listen to Korah’s defiant attitude
toward Moses
ビデオの中で見られるコラの
反抗的な態度に注目してください
as taken
from Numbers chapter 16.
There’s Moses.
That is enough of you
because the whole assembly
are all of them holy
and Jehovah is in their midst.
Why, then, should you lift yourselves up
above the congregation of Jehovah?
Korah and the others
made great pretenses of loyalty to God,
コラとほかの者たちは
神に忠節なふりをしていましたが—
but completely ignored the fact
エホバが直接モーセとアロンを
任命したことを無視していました
that Jehovah directly appointed
Moses and Aaron.
では実際にはだれに
つぶやいていたのでしょうか？
Who, then, were
they really murmuring against?
民数記 26:9をご覧ください
Notice Numbers 26:9:
“このダタンとアビラムは
集会に呼ばれたものでー”
“This Dathan and Abiram
were chosen ones of the assembly
“コラの集会に連なって
モーセとアロンに対するー”
“who fought against Moses
and Aaron along with Korah’s group
“争いに加わった者たちである”
“そのさい彼らはエホバに対する
争いに加わったのである”
when they fought against Jehovah.”
While focusing on the man Moses
and his imperfections,
モーセとその不完全さに
注目する一方で—
エホバがイスラエル国民を
導いておられることを見失ったのです
they did not really see that it was Jehovah
who was directing the nation.
実際にはエホバと争っていたのです
They were actually fighting
against Jehovah.
神の任命した人に対する
不忠節の結果は死でした
Their disloyalty to God’s appointed men
cost them their lives.
しかしコラの子たちは
異なる決定をしました
But Korah’s sons
made a different choice.
次のビデオクリップで父親とは
全く異なる態度に注目してください
In this next clip, notice an attitude
far different from their father’s.
My father and his companions
actually rebelled
against Jehovah’s authority.
Their envy, pride,
and ambition led to rebellion,
and in the end they brought
dishonor upon themselves.
My father sought glory,
but his glory was short-lived.
I’m glad, though, that my brothers
and I took the right side of the issue.
It must have been hard though.
Yes, it was.
But that helps us to understand
how important it is
that we do not allow
friendships or family
to take priority
over our relationship with Jehovah
and our obedience to him.
That’s what Father
has always told me.
Mmm, yes.
Ultimately, successful direction
for us humans
comes from Jehovah.
We should completely trust
in his choices of appointed ones.
You see, respect for those
whom Jehovah has appointed
shows respect
for Jehovah’s authority.
The loyalty displayed by Korah’s sons
エホバはコラの子たちが示した
忠節に動かされ—
moved Jehovah to act
in loyalty by sparing their lives.
忠節に彼らの命を救われました
What fine examples
for us to imitate!
見倣うべき立派な模範です
エホバの民を導くよう
今日任命されている人々に—
May we never find ourselves
fighting against Jehovah
つぶやいたり不平を言ったりして—
by murmuring
or complaining against those
決してエホバと争う者に
ならないようにしたいものです
who he has appointed
to lead his people today.
To see more
of the good and the bad examples
忠節に関する良い例や悪い例について
もっと知るためJW Broadcastingで
of loyalty
among the Israelites,
we encourage you to watch the entire
Respect Jehovah’s Authority video
「エホバの権威に敬意を示す」のビデオ
全体をご覧になるようお勧めします
on JW Broadcasting.
In review, how can we show
our loyalty to Jehovah?
エホバに対する忠節をどのように
示せるか振り返ってみましょう
First, by coming to his defense
as his Witnesses.
第一にその方の証人として
エホバを擁護する
Second, by maintaining our loyal support
第二に“忠実で思慮深い奴隷”を
忠節に支持し続ける
of “the faithful and discreet slave.”
第三に任命された長老たちの指示に
忠節に従う
And third, by loyally following direction
from the appointed elders.
As you imitate faithful examples
like the sons of Korah,
コラの子たち ダビデ ペテロ—
またパウロなどの忠実な
模範に倣うなら—
like David, Peter, and Paul,
あなたはエホバから
忠節な人とみなされ—
you will prove to be someone
Jehovah views as loyal
エホバの忠節な行ないを
永遠に受けるに—
—worthy of receiving
his acts of loyalty forever.
ふさわしい人になることが
できるでしょう
Our second point on loyalty
2番目の点は—
忠実で思慮深い奴隷の指示に
従う方法を示していました
shows us ways we can follow
the faithful and discreet slave’s direction.
But have you ever wondered how
統治体がどのように—
重要な決定に至るのか
考えたことがありますか？
the Governing Body arrives
at important decisions?
ベテルの朝の崇拝で—
In this Bethel morning worship,
デービッド・スプレーン兄弟が
答えています
Brother David Splane
answers that very question.
“Well, there’ve been so many changes.
“次々と変化や変更があって
ついていくのが大変だ”
It’s hard to keep up.”
We hear that a lot.
そんなことをよく耳にします
And it’s true.
では 少し考えてみましょう
So the question is,
How do these changes come about?
これらの変更は
どのように生じるのでしょうか
Does the Governing Body get together
on a Wednesday morning and say,
統治体が水曜日の朝に集まって—
“Well, what will we change
this week?
“さあ 今週はどんな変更を加えて
兄弟たちを驚かせようか”—
Let’s throw the brotherhood
off guard a little bit.”
などと話し合うのでしょうか？
That would not be
faithful or discreet.
それでは 忠実で思慮深いとは
いえません
The fact is that,
次々に変更が加えられる
ように思えても—
although changes may seem
to be announced one after another,
実際には その決定に何年も費やされて
いることが少なくありません
the decision to put
the changes into effect
is often years in the making.
Now, one of the first big changes
例えば 現在の統治体が最初に
取り組んだ大きな変更のひとつは—
that the current Governing Body
had to grapple with
had to do with this,
米国に支部委員会を置いて 機能させる
ことができるかということでした
Is it feasible
to have a Branch Committee serving
in the United States?
Now, for years the thought was
that we really couldn’t have
長年 それは難しいと
考えられてきました
a Branch Committee
functioning in the United States
なぜなら米国には 統治体と世界本部の
双方が置かれてきたからです
because the States was host
to the Governing Body
and the world headquarters.
So this was going to be
a big decision,
これは大きな決定でしたし—
一日で決まるようなことでも
ありませんでした
and it wasn’t taken overnight.
A lot of consultation
円熟し 経験を積んだ兄弟たちの
助言も必要でした
with mature,
experienced brothers was necessary.
But finally the decision was made,
しかし 最終的には決定が下され—
and we believe that decision
has had Jehovah’s rich blessing.
エホバはその決定を豊かに
祝福してこられました
We’re proud
of our hard-working Branch Committee,
わたしたちは 支部委員会の熱心な
働きと支えに感謝しています
and we’re happy
to have their support.
彼らの支えを必要としています
We need their support.
Now let’s consider
a couple of other examples.
別の例も 幾つか取り上げましょう
Beginning in the first week
of January 2009,
2009年1月の最初の週から—
神権宣教学校 奉仕会 そして
書籍研究が一つになりました
the School, Service Meeting,
and the Congregation Book Study
were merged.
Now that decision
その決定には
10年ほどが費やされました
was almost ten years
in the making.
1999年にはすでに そのことが
話し合われていたからです
As far back as 1999,
it was being discussed.
Well, then, why wasn’t the decision
made ten years earlier?
ではなぜ そのときに決定が
下されなかったのでしょうか？
Because the Governing Body
wanted to be sure.
統治体は これらの集会を
一つにまとめても—
Will the brothers
have what they need?
兄弟たちが必要とする
霊的食物を—
Will they have
all of the spiritual food they need
供給できるかどうかを確かめたいと
思っていたのです
if we merge the meetings?
Now then one Wednesday
ある水曜日のこと
確か3時半ごろだったと思いますが—
—I think it was
about three-thirty in the afternoon—
we’d had a long meeting.
会議が長引いているところに —
We received two letters
from large branches.
二つの大きな支部から
手紙が届きました
And one of the branches said
that they had many large congregations
一つの支部によれば
七つか八つの書籍研究があるのに—
with seven or eight book studies,
長老と奉仕の僕が一人ずつしか
いないような大きな会衆が—
but with only one elder
and one ministerial servant.
幾つもあって—
So the elder might conduct
five book studies,
長老が五つ 奉仕の僕が三つ
という具合に書籍研究を司会し—
and the ministerial servant
might conduct three,
and then they had all of the parts
on the meetings to prepare.
その上で他の集会の準備も
行なっていました
So all they were doing with their time
was conducting book studies
それらの兄弟たちは 書籍研究の司会と
集会の準備で精一杯でした
and preparing parts
for the meetings.
It was hard!
別の支部から受け取った
手紙には—
And then the same week we received
a letter from another branch,
書籍研究の出席者が減っている
理由が書かれていました
and they explained why the attendance
at the book study was so low.
They explained that the publishers
loved the meetings
手紙によると 奉仕者たちは—
書籍研究を含め すべての集会を
大切にしているものの—
—all of the meetings—
including the book study.
But they’re very poor,
and they couldn’t afford the bus fare
あまりの貧しさゆえに 週日の
二つの集会にバスで行く費用を賄えず—
to attend two midweek meetings;
they had to choose.
どちらかを選ばなければならない
とのことでした
And if they attended
the School and Service Meeting,
学校と奉仕会の集会に出れば—
they could get almost two hours
of spiritual direction,
霊的な指導を2時間受けられるのに—
whereas with the book study,
they would get one.
書籍研究では1時間です
So most of the time
it was the School
それで 多くの場合—
学校と奉仕会の集会が選ばれました
and Service Meeting
that won out.
Well, those two letters
これら二通の手紙は—
わたしたちが
兄弟たちの実情を理解し—
put a real face
on the situation,
決定を下すうえで
助けとなりました
and it helped us
to make the decision.
Now, in 2008,
さて 2008年から—
a public edition
and a study edition
一般用と研究用の「ものみの塔」誌が
発行されるようになりました
of The Watchtower
began to be published.
この決定にも
長い時間がかかりました
That decision was
a long time coming.
何度も話し合いましたが—
We discussed the possibility off and on,
but we always said,
”性急にならず
少し待ってみよう—”
“Let’s not be hasty;
let’s wait a little bit.
“エホバは何を望まれるだろうか？”
と考えました
Let’s see what Jehovah wants.”
The main thing was,
What would Jehovah want?
大切なのは
エホバが何を望まれるか—
And how would we know?
それを どのように見極めるか？
ということでした
We decided to make
a sort of fleece test.
それで ”羊毛の試み”を
することにしました
And so in 2006,
2006年に「目ざめよ！」誌を
月1回の発行とし—
we began publishing
one Awake! a month,
「ものみの塔」誌は
引き続き月2回の発行としました
but we kept publishing
two Watchtowers.
So that would be three magazines
per month, instead of four.
月に4冊ではなく 3冊の雑誌が
発行されるようにしたのです
And the rationale was,
“We’ll try it for a year,
そして—
“and if at the end of a year
“一年間試して 雑誌の配布が
急激に落ち込むようだったら—”
“our magazine placements
have plummeted,
“we’ll know that Jehovah
is not backing this arrangement.
“エホバの支持はなかったと考えて—”
“「目ざめよ！」誌を月2回の
発行に戻そう”と考えました
We can go back to producing
two Awakes! a year.”
Well, what was the result?
結果はどうでしたか？
At the end of the year,
前年に 月4冊発行されていたとき
と同じくらいの配布が—
we were placing
as many magazines at three per month
as we had been placing
at four per month the year before.
月3冊でも
みられたのです
それで エホバが
新たな取り決めを—
So that indicated to us
支持してくださっていることが
わかりました
that Jehovah
was backing the arrangement.
And how many
of us have appreciated
皆さんも 兄弟たちに直接的に
語りかける研究用と—
having a study edition
of The Watchtower
that speaks directly
to the brotherhood
一般の人たちの必要に合わせた
一般用の両方の備えに—
and then a public edition
of The Watchtower
that can be tailored
a little bit more
to the needs of the public.
感謝しておられるでしょう
Now, before making
any decision
王国の業に影響を及ぼす
どんな決定を下すときにも—
that affects
the Kingdom work,
the Governing Body
has to carefully consider
統治体は 霊的な面でもたらされる
結果を考慮します
the spiritual implications.
As an example,
in 2008,
例えば 2008年に公開講演の長さが
45分から30分へと変更になりました
the decision was made to reduce
the length of public talks
from 45 minutes
to 30 minutes.
この決定は 兄弟たちにどんな
霊的な影響を与えたでしょうか？
Well you say, ‘How could
that decision possibly affect
the spirituality
of the brotherhood?’
もし皆さんが 長老の大勢いる
都市部の会衆にいて—
And if you’re serving
in an urban congregation with many elders
近隣の会衆にも
長老が大勢いる場合—
and nearby there are other
urban congregations with many elders,
この調整の意図が
分かりにくいかもしれません
perhaps you’d have difficulty
in understanding the reasoning.
しかし 統治体は物事の
全体を見ています
But the Governing Body
has to look at the whole picture.
Thousands of our brothers
have served where the need is great,
大勢の兄弟たちが必要の大きな会衆で
働いていて 外国語を学んでいます
and they’ve learned
a foreign language.
そうした会衆の多くでは
長老たちも言語を学習中です
And in many, many
of these congregations
the learners are the elders.
Some of the learners
have told us
ある兄弟たちは 公開講演を1分準備する
のに1時間かかると言っていました
that for every minute
of a public talk,
it has required one hour
of preparation.
ということは
45分の公開講演の準備に—
So can you imagine:
45-minute public talk
合計45時間を費やす
ことになります
—45 hours for some of them?
So the reduction in the length
of the public talks has actually meant
ですから講演の長さを
短くするなら—
これらの会衆でより多くの
公開講演を提供できるでしょう
that these congregations
could have more public talks.
That’s not all.
さらに 孤立した会衆で
奉仕する長老もいて—
There are thousands of elders
who are serving
in isolated congregations
隣の会衆まで100キロ以上も
離れている場合があります
that may be 100 miles or more
from the next congregation.
ある会衆に
一人の長老がいて—
So in one congregation
you have one elder,
100キロほど先の会衆に別の長老が
一人いるという具合です
and then 100 miles away you have
another congregation with one elder.
これらの兄弟たちが
協力し合っても—
How many public talks
were those brothers getting
45分なら どれほどの公開講演を
提供できるでしょうか？
when there were
45-minute public talks?
The 15-minute reduction
made a difference.
15分の短縮が
違いをもたらします
So if we take a narrow view
もし視野が狭く
自分の置かれている状況や—
and think only about our own situation
and our own congregation,
自分の会衆のことしか
考慮に入れないとすれば—
well, we can have difficulty
in understanding
特定の決定が下された理由が
分かりにくいかもしれません
why certain decisions are made.
Now the same principles
apply to clarifications in our beliefs.
このことは教義の解明にも
あてはまります
The Governing Body loves
to get together and discuss the Bible.
統治体は 集まりあって 聖書に
ついて討議するのが大好きです
And when those Bibles
come out on the table
聖書を取り出し それぞれが
調査した事柄を持ち寄り—
and when the brothers
bring their research in
and they’re starting to search
the Scriptures and analyze the Scriptures,
聖句について調べ 分析しはじめると
兄弟たちには笑顔があふれます
you see the happy smiles
on their faces.
The brothers love
discussing spiritual things.
霊的な事柄を話し合うことを
愛しているからです
But the clarifications
しかし 新たな解明が示されるときには
長い時間がかけられます
are often a long time
in coming into print.
Why?
なぜでしょうか?
Because the clarification
on one scripture
一つの聖句の解明はドミノのように
他の箇所にも影響を及ぼすからです
can have
a domino effect on others.
The clarification
on one scripture
新たな解明が他の預言に影響を
及ぼすこともあるので—
can have ramifications
on other prophecies,
so we have to be absolutely sure
that everything fits.
関係するすべての要素が
調和しているという確信が必要です
So to reiterate,
although certain changes
may be announced one after another,
このように 次々に
変更が発表されるとしても
these decisions
are thought out very carefully.
それらは 注意深く
考え抜かれているのです
And here’s
an interesting side point:
興味深いことに—
The older members
of the Governing Body
ジャラズ兄弟やバー兄弟のような
統治体の年長の成員は—
—Brother Jaracz, Brother Barr—
were just as interested
in making the adjustments
若い成員と同じほど 変化を生み出す
ことに関心を持っていました
as the younger members were.
兄弟たちは 非常に進歩的でした
They were very progressive.
What an insight into the faithful
and discreet slave’s loving concern!
忠実で思慮深い奴隷の愛ある気遣いを
感じさせるコメントです
Did you hear things
the Governing Body does
統治体が行なっている
事柄を聞いて—
that would further motivate you
to support and follow their direction?
その指示に一層従いたいと
思いましたか？
Perhaps it’s how
they consulted experienced brothers;
統治体は
経験ある兄弟たちに相談し—
世界中の兄弟たちの
異なる状況を考え—
or that they consider our brothers’
varying circumstances worldwide;
最も重要なこととして—
or, most importantly,
how they patiently and prayerfully seek
辛抱強く祈りのうちに
エホバのご意志を知り—
自分たちの決定の上に
祝福を求めているのです
to know Jehovah’s will
and look for his blessing on a decision.
Millions of our brothers
and sisters around the world
世界中の兄弟姉妹たちは—
エホバと組織に忠節を
示すことからくる—
can recount
the blessings they’ve gained
by remaining loyal
to Jehovah and his organization.
祝福を詳しく
話すことができます
今日ここにそのようなお二人を
お招きしています
And we’re privileged to have
two such examples here with us today:
ウィリアム・マレンフォント兄弟と
妻のサンドラ姉妹です
Brother and Sister
William and Sandra Malenfant.
Brother Malenfant is a helper
to the Teaching Committee,
マレンフォント兄弟は
教育委員会の援助者で—
and Sister Malenfant’s current assignment
is in the Service Department.
マレンフォント姉妹は現在
奉仕部門で働いています
And we’re looking forward to hearing
お二人のすばらしい霊的な
歩みについて伺いましょう
about their rich spiritual history.
So, Bill and Sandra,
we’re so happy
スタジオにお越しいただき
うれしく思います
that we could have you
here in the studio with us,
お二人をさらに知ることができる
のを楽しみにしています
and we do look forward
to learning more about you.
Maybe we would like
to go back.
過去にさかのぼって—
How did you get
on the road that has led you
長年にわたるエホバへの
忠実で忠節な奉仕の道を—
to so many years of faithful,
loyal service to Jehovah?
どのように
歩み始められましたか？
It was back in 1954.
1954年のことです
母は数年間 時々エホバの証人と
連絡をとっていました
My mother had contact on and off
with the Witnesses for years.
I was about 20 years old,
わたしが20歳のころです
and she was invited
to a public talk
母はカリフォルニア州
オークランド・セントラル会衆の—
at the Oakland Central Congregation
in California.
公開講演に招待されました
She asked me,
“Would you accompany me?”
一緒に来るかと尋ねられ
“うん 行くよ”と答えました
And I said: “Yeah.
Sure, I’ll be happy to go.”
その集会に高校のころからの
知り合いがいました
Well, I recognized a young man
I knew from high school at the meeting,
あとから近づいてきて
聖書研究が必要だと言われました
and he approached me after
and told me I needed a Bible study.
I really didn’t want a Bible study,
but he insisted,
乗り気ではなかったんですが—
強く勧められたので—
and so I said,
“Well, you can come by.”
“じゃあ来ていいよ”と言ったんです
Would you believe it?
「神を真とすべし」の本で研究が始まり—
I started a Bible study
in the “Let God Be True” book.
4か月後にバプテスマを受けました
Four months later,
I was baptized.
これこそまさに自分が
求めていたものだったのに—
It was exactly what I was looking for,
but I didn’t realize it.
気づかなかったんです
Good choice.
Thank you.
良い選択ですね
And, Sandra, your start on the road
サンドラ姉妹の
スタートはいかがですか？
to a career serving Jehovah?
Before I was born, my parents
started on this search for the truth.
わたしが生まれる前
両親は真理を探していました
It happened because they
had lost a little girl in death,
幼い娘を亡くしたからです
and they went from church to church
looking for some kind of comfort.
慰めを求めに
幾つもの教会に行きました
And, of course, the clergy
had no comfort for them.
もちろん 聖職者は
何の慰めにもならず—
They just said, “Well, God wanted
another angel in heaven.”
“神は天使をもう一人望まれたのですよ”と
言うだけでした
And that angered my father.
He thought: ‘No.
父は怒って
“そんなはずはない！”
‘If God wants another angel,
he can make one.
“もし必要なら神は造ることが
おできになる”
He wouldn’t take my little girl!’
So it just happened
“娘を取り去るはずはない！”
と思いました
that one evening
they were listening to the radio
ある晩 両親は
ラジオを聞いていました
—long before TV, of course—
and they heard
a Jehovah’s Witness give a talk.
そこでエホバの証人の話を聞きました
その題は「死者はどこにいるか」でした
And the title of that talk was
“Where Are the Dead?”
想像してみてください
Imagine!
He gave all the Scriptural proof
about the condition of the dead
死者の状態 復活の希望について
すべて聖書から証明したんです
and the hope for the resurrection.
And my father immediately said,
“This is the truth!”
父はすぐに
「これこそ真理だ！」と言いました
So they wrote
to the radio station;
それでラジオ局に手紙を書き
話の小冊子を手に入れ—
got a copy
of the booklet of the talk;
and then, also,
they started receiving
「ものみの塔」誌の
予約購読を始めました
the subscription
to The Watchtower.
でもわたしが生まれて
3歳になった時に初めて—
But it wasn’t until I was born
and three years old
that the Witnesses
finally made contact with us.
ある証人の家族に会えたんです
So, what motivated you
to make a choice
全時間奉仕を選び—
人生をエホバに捧げるきっかけと
なったものは何でしょうか？
to get into the full-time service
and give your life to Jehovah?
Well, what motivated me
56年の大会に出席したことです
was when I attended
a convention, also in ’56.
54年にバプテスマを受け—
I got baptized in ’54.
56年のカリフォルニア州
オールバニーの地域大会に行きました
But in ’56, I went to a district convention
in Albany, California,
そこに開拓者ブースがあったんです
and there was a pioneer booth.
So I approached the booth,
and an older sister there looked at me
ブースに近づくと
年長の姉妹がわたしを見て—
and said:
“You’re young and strong.
“あなたは若くて強いのに
なぜ開拓者でないの？”と言いました
Why aren’t you a pioneer?”
I felt, ‘Well, yes.
Why not?’
“そうだ なぜだろう?”と思い
1956年に開拓を始めました
So I started
pioneering in 1956.
That’s what motivated me.
それがきっかけです
And I was—
Really, I look back at that;
振り返ると これは
人生の最善の決定でした
it was one of the best decisions
I made in my life.
Sandra, how about you?
サンドラ姉妹のきっかけは
何でしょうか？
Motivated to get
into full-time service.
Well, for pioneer service, you know,
it was—it was like a given.
開拓奉仕を行なうのは
当然のことでした
Young people were
just encouraged to pioneer.
若い人はそう
励まされていたんです
And most of the young people
were doing that.
ほとんどの若者が
そうしていたんです
You know, after a year or two, maybe they
would get married and start a family.
1, 2年後結婚して
家族を持つかもしれません
But those years in pioneering
—starting out their life that way—
でも開拓奉仕の年月は—
残りの人生で忠実な奉仕をするための
素晴らしい土台となるんです
gave them a wonderful basis
for loyal service the rest of their life.
Beautiful.
素晴らしいですね
So you were pioneering.
開拓をして どのようにお二人は
出会ったんでしょうか？
How did your paths
eventually meet?
It was at a circuit assembly
1956年 カリフォルニア州
オークランドでの巡回大会で—
in Oakland, California, 1956.
とても興味深いことが起きたんです
Very interesting things
took place.
I had the job
of dismantling the stage.
わたしはステージを解体していました
And I was carrying
this large piece of plywood off the stage,
ステージから大きなベニヤ板を
運んでいると—
and I ran right into Sandra
and knocked her flat!
サンドラにぶつかって
倒してしまいました
Well, I took advantage
of the opportunity.
“いい自己紹介の仕方ではないな”と
思いながらも—
I thought, ‘Well, that’s not
the best way to introduce yourself.’
この機会を利用して—
But I said, “By the way,
would you like to accompany me
“ところで 友人との集いに
一緒に来ませんか？”と言いました
to a get-together
some of the friends are having?”
Very good, Bill.
良かったですね
Well, yes,
and I followed through on it.
ええ そして
言ったとおりにしました
We had a lot
of association,
たくさん交わり
数カ月後 結婚しました
and after a number of months,
we got married.
And both of us
were pioneering
二人とも開拓奉仕をして
エホバに仕え とても幸福でした
—very happy in our ministry
serving Jehovah.
You really swept her off her feet.
Literally.
姉妹は兄弟に惚れたんですね？
ええ
I fell for him.
良かったですね！
Very good.
So, shortly after you were married,
結婚してすぐ
指示に応じられたと聞いております
I understand
that you received some direction.
ええ 結婚してまだ1か月ほど
だったと思いますが—
Yes, the circuit overseer
visited our congregation.
We were only married about a month,
I think, when he came through.
—巡回訪問がありました
—そうね
And he told us that the organization
was looking for pioneers
組織は 特別開拓者としてどこでも
特にアメリカの必要の大きな場所で—
who’d be willing to serve
as special pioneers and go wherever,
喜んで奉仕する開拓者を
探しているとのことでした
where the need was great
in the United States particularly.
“もちろん 喜んでそうします”
と言いました
So we told him:
“Sure. We’d be delighted to do it.”
And four months
after our marriage,
結婚して4か月後
アイオワ州ディコーラで—
we received an assignment
as special pioneers to Decorah, Iowa.
特別開拓者として奉仕する
割り当てを受けました
Now, that was
a very interesting place
会衆に8人の伝道者しかいない
とても興味深い場所です
because there were
only eight publishers in the congregation.
But we arrived
到着して王国会館での
集会から始めました
and started with the meetings there
at the Kingdom Hall.
王国会館はディコーラ中心部にある
ハント雑貨店の上にあり—
And the Kingdom Hall was up
above Hunt’s Variety Store
in downtown Decorah,
and we lived in a room behind it.
わたしたちはその裏の部屋に
住んでいました
Well, you know,
you’re on your own like that
周りに大勢の兄弟がおらず—
—not a lot of brothers around—
自分でなんとかしていると
励ましと仲間が欲しくなります
so you look
for encouragement and company.
And we would travel down
to Strawberry Point, Iowa,
それでアイオワ州
ストロベリー・ポイントまで行っていました
to where
Charles and Shirley Sinutko lived
そこにチャールズ・シナツコ
とシャーリーが—
in a log cabin
—one-room log cabin.
ワンルームの丸太小屋に
住んでいたんです
And we’d go visit with them in order
to have some mutual encouragement.
励まし合うためによく行きましたよ
It’s a nice picture of you
in that log cabin too
その頃の丸太小屋での
素敵な写真です
as you were
special pioneering.
業に忙しくしておられました
So you’re busy
in that work.
どんな特別な招待を
受けられましたか？
What special invitation
did you receive?
Well, we received
the invitation to attend Gilead
第34期ギレアデ学校への
招待を受けました
—the 34th class of Gilead School—
アイオワ州で2年半特別開拓奉仕を
したあとの素晴らしい出来事です
and that was a wonderful thing
after two and half years of pioneering,
special pioneering in Iowa.
レバノンが任地でしたが
ビザを取得できず入れませんでした
And we were assigned
to Lebanon,
but we were unable to enter Lebanon
because we couldn’t get the visa.
それで組織から—
“モロッコでの割り当てを受け入れますか？”
と尋ねられました
So, then, the organization
asked us,
“Well, will you take
an assignment to Morocco?”
どこにでも行くつもりでした
We were ready to go anywhere.
それでニューヨーク市から船に乗り—
So that’s how we took
a boat from New York City
5日かけて大西洋を横断し
カサブランカに到着しました
—five days across the Atlantic—
to Casablanca.
Very nice.
いいですね
Well, what was it like to be
in the missionary service in Morocco?
モロッコでの宣教者奉仕は
いかがでしたか？
It was very interesting.
とても興味深く
本当に楽しみました
We really enjoyed it.
But, you know, we only spoke English.
英語しか話せなかったので
フランス語を学ぶ必要がありました
So in Morocco,
we had to learn French.
And the first month
of our missionary service in Morocco,
モロッコでの宣教奉仕の最初の月—
for 30 days we studied
the language 11 hours a day.
30日の間 一日11時間
言語を勉強しました
Well, that could get pretty tiring
for 11 hours a day,
とても疲れるので
フランス映画を見に行き—
so we’d go to the French movies
and count that as language time.
その時間も言語の時間に
数えたんです
And then, we were moved
to Tangier.
それから タンジールに移動しました
And there was
a Spanish congregation in Tangier,
そこにはスペイン語会衆があり
スペイン語も勉強しなければなりません
so we had to learn
the Spanish language too.
But that was
really a rich blessing
でも その文化に触れ 奉仕できたのは
本当に大きな祝福でした
for the two of us
to be exposed to that culture
and to have
that privilege of serving there.
So after four years, I understand
that you came back to visit your family.
4年後 家族に会うために
帰国されました
その後 どんな試練となる
出来事があったでしょうか？
What events
were challenging thereafter?
I think Sandra can relate that.
その点はサンドラが話します
Well, it was
usually permitted
通常4年間任地にいると
休暇をとって帰省し—
that after you were
in your assignment four years,
then you were allowed
to come home
家族に会うことができました
and at least have a vacation
and visit your family.
But we got back.
帰国して 家族に会いました
We visited our family,
and while there,
健康診断を受けると—
深刻な健康上の問題を抱えている
ことがわかったんです
I had a medical examination and found out
that I had a serious health problem.
もちろん 費用をまかなえるだけの
蓄えはありません
Of course, we didn’t have
the funds to cover that.
それでビルが協会に手紙を書き
取り決めが設けられました
So Bill wrote to the Society,
and we made arrangements.
They said,
“Well, just take care of your situation,
“まず状況に対処してください”
“元気になったら連絡してください”
と言われました
and let us know when you’re free.”
So he got a job
to take care
それで ビルは医療上の必要と
生活のために仕事を見つけました
of our medical needs
as well as living conditions.
でも 本当に自分たちは
駄目な人間だと感じたんです
But you know,
we just felt like we were failures.
Jehovah knew
we were discouraged.
エホバはわたしたちが落胆し
動揺していることをご存知でした
He knew we felt
distraught about this.
So he knew just what we needed,
and he gave it to us.
何が必要か知っておられ
それを与えてくださったんです
As I got to feeling better
and we got more free
in our use of time,
体調が良くなり
時間に余裕が出てきたので—
開拓を始めました
we started pioneering.
And Jehovah blessed
our ministry just incredibly.
エホバは宣教を
祝福してくださいました
信じられないほどにです
There were times,
in this supposedly “unproductive territory”
“産出的ではない”と
思われていた区域で—
25人も集会に出席した
ことがあります
that we had up to 25 people
attending the meetings.
その多くがバプテスマを受け
今でも良い友人です
Many of them got baptized,
and they’re our fast friends to this day.
すごいですね
That’s incredible!
So Jehovah knows what you need,
and he provides it.
エホバは必要をご存知で
備えてくださるんです
素晴らしいです
That is beautiful!
帰国して困難に対処する間—
What temptation
did you have to resist
どんな誘惑を退ける必要が
あったでしょうか？
when you came back
and were going through these difficulties?
Well, I think it’s
a temptation that confronts
これは健康上の理由で戻る兄弟姉妹の
多くが直面する誘惑だと思います
a lot of brothers and sisters
who return because of health reasons,
状況ゆえに落ち着く
兄弟たちもおられますが—
and some just end up settling down
because of their circumstances.
誘惑となるのは—
“家に帰ってきた”
But the temptation there was:
‘Well, you’re home.
“もう何年もモロッコで奉仕した”
‘You’ve already done your service
in Morocco for a number of years.
“全時間宣教を行なった”
“今は落ち着こう 家を買おう”
と考えることです
‘You’ve been
in the full-time ministry.
Just settle down now.
Buy a house.’
でもそれはわたしたちの
願いではありませんでした
But really,
that wasn’t our desire.
サンドラの体調が良くなると
すぐ開拓を始め 本部に手紙を書きました
So as soon as Sandra
got on her feet
and was feeling well enough,
we got pioneering.
And then I wrote headquarters,
and I said: ‘Here we are.
“ここにわたしたちがおります
何でも果たせます”
‘We’re ready to take on whatever.
“何ができるでしょうか？”
What would you like us to do?’
Good example.
Thank you.
よい模範ですね
So you made yourself
available to the organization.
組織で自分を役立たせ
次はどこに遣わされたのでしょうか？
Where did they send you next?
A wonderful assignment.
素晴らしい割り当てです
We were sent
as special pioneers to Washington D.C.,
特別開拓者として
ワシントンDCに遣わされました
to help start
a Spanish congregation.
スペイン語会衆の設立を手伝うためです
非常に豊かな祝福となりました
And that was indeed
a very rich blessing.
そこにいた1年半で
小さな会衆が設立されたんです
We were there
a year and a half
until that little congregation
was solid and was formed.
別の祝福も受け
巡回奉仕に割り当てられました
And then we received
another blessing.
フロリダ州のキー･ウエストから
オルランドまでの—
We were appointed
to the circuit work.
So I had the Spanish circuit in Florida
アメリカで一つの
スペイン語巡回区です
from Key West to Orlando
—one circuit in the whole state.
それからニューヨーク市に来て
ブロンクスに住みました
Then we came to New York City
—lived in the Bronx.
巡回区を持ち スペイン語の
野外で地域奉仕をしました
I had a circuit, and we did
district work in the Spanish field.
それから テキサス州の谷と呼ばれる—
Then, to Texas
テキサス州リオグランデ･バレーの
巡回区で数年奉仕しました
—to what they call the Valley of Texas,
the Rio Grande Valley—
for a couple of years in the circuit.
その次は テキサス州
ヒューストンから—
Then the district in Spanish
カリフォルニア州ユバシティまでの
スペイン語地域区です
from Houston, Texas,
to Yuba City, California.
心から楽しみました
And we loved
every minute of it.
Well, that’s definitely
the traveling work.
まさに旅行する奉仕ですね
Then 1977 rolls around
and you receive another invitation.
1977年に別の招待を受けられました
そのとおりです！
Yes, indeed!
We were doing
preconvention work
レイマート大会ホールでロサンゼルスの
地域大会の準備をしていました
in the L.A. area
at the Leimert Assembly Hall,
and we received a letter
inviting us to come to Bethel.
すると ベテルへの招待の手紙を
受け取ったんです
ベテルに招待されるのは
本当に 本当に特別な特権です
That was a very, very special privilege:
to be invited to Bethel.
当時 大勢の旅行する監督が
奉仕部門に入り働いていたので—
I went into the Service Department,
because at that time they
invited a number of traveling overseers
わたしも奉仕部門に入り
サンドラはハウスキーパーになりました
to come in and work
in the Service Department,
and Sandra went
into housekeeping.
And we were both
delighted to come to Bethel.
二人ともベテルに来て喜びました
Well, sort of.
まあ そうね...
I really loved the ministry;
わたしは宣教を本当に愛していました
I loved, especially,
the district work
特に 地域奉仕で毎週
巡回監督やその妻と—
—being with
the circuit overseer and his wife
every week
and out in service.
一緒に奉仕するのが
好きだったんです
So I wasn’t too anxious
for this Bethel thing.
それで ベテルでの奉仕を切望していた
というわけではありませんでした
But, you know.
Jehovah, again, knows what you need.
でも エホバは今回も
必要なことをご存知だったんです
We came here, and we
started adjusting to Bethel life.
ここに来て ベテルでの生活に
慣れ始めると—
And it really proved out
to be a real blessing
これがいかに大きな祝福か
ということがわかりました
because we got
the close association
たくさんのエホバの忠実な証人と
親しい交わりを持てたからです
with so many
other loyal Witnesses of Jehovah.
Well, I’m sure you
have many more experiences
ほかにもたくさんあると
思いますが—
to let us know about,
but we appreciate you sharing those.
幾つか話してくださり
ありがとうございます
The Governing Body
has made significant adjustments
統治体はベテルと野外の業に
大きな調整を行ない—
in the work that is taking place
at Bethel and the field,
多くの長年の忠実で忠節な兄弟たち—
and it has affected
many long-time faithful brothers
旅行する兄弟たちや会衆の監督
ベテルの監督に影響がありました
—loyal brothers
in the traveling work,
overseers in the congregation,
overseers at Bethel.
Bill, what do you think
about some of these changes
統治体が最近行なった変更について
どうお感じですか？
that the Governing Body
has made recently?
とても賢明な決定だと思います
I think they’re
very wise decisions.
They know what is needed;
統治体は何が必要か
知っており—
they appreciate the older men
who have served for years.
長年奉仕した年長の男子に
感謝しています
We know that the older brothers
in circuit work, district work,
巡回奉仕や地域奉仕
あるいはどこであれ—
wherever, they’re “worthy of double honor”
because of the way
業に自分を費やしてきた兄弟たちは
“二倍の誉れに値”します
they’ve given
of themselves to the work.
But we have to recognize, too,
there comes a time
でも より若い人たちが来て—
when we want the younger men
to come along,
責任を担うべき時が来ることも
認めなければなりません
to accept responsibility.
実際 わたしたちが若かった頃は—
And, really,
when we were young,
ほんの少しの背景と訓練で
責任を担っていました
we received responsibilities
with very little background and training.
今は王国福音宣明者のための学校や
王国宣教学校があります
Now we’ve got all these schools
for Kingdom Evangelizers
and the Kingdom Ministry School.
若い人が訓練を受ける
多くの機会があるんです
So many opportunities
for younger ones to be trained.
それで素晴らしい取り決めだと思います
And so I think
it’s a wonderful arrangement.
大勢の若い男子は
とてもよくやっており—
Many thousands of young men
are doing so well,
責任を担う準備ができています
ready to accept responsibility.
組織全体にとっての祝福です
It’s a blessing
for the entire organization.
Well, thank you for sharing that.
ありがとうございます
That’ll benefit many brothers.
多くの兄弟たちが益を受けます
So we look
at this couple before us,
お二人について—
また賢明な決定を下してきた
兄弟姉妹について知ることができました
and we see some who have made
wise choices along the way.
So we look back at over 60 years
of faithful, loyal service.
60年以上に及ぶ忠実で忠節な
奉仕を振り返りました
As you look back at decisions
人生の決定に
後悔がおありでしょうか？
you made in life, any regrets?
Oh, absolutely none!
全くありません
We consider that whatever
あきらめたことや行ったことは—
we have given up or done
it’s been our gift to Jehovah.
みなエホバへのプレゼントと考えています
You know, when I was a little girl,
I remember I used to go out on our farm
まだ少女だった頃 農場に出て—
and, especially when there
was a full moon, I used to pray to Jehovah.
特に満月の時には
エホバに祈りこう言いました
And I’d say,
“わたしの人生すべてを
あなたの奉仕に用いてください”
“Just let me use up my life in your service.”
エホバは祈りに答えてくださり—
You know, he’s answered
that prayer because my life,
わたしは人生の大半を—
エホバへの奉仕に
費やすことができました
the majority of it, is used up
and he’s let me do it in his service.
素敵ですね
Beautiful.
兄弟は歩みにおける犠牲を
どう見ておられますか？
Bill, how do you view sacrifices
that you have made along the way?
Well, as you know, a sacrifice
神に仕えるためにあきらめたことは
犠牲と言えるかもしれません
can be something
you give up to serve God, perhaps.
エホバに差し出すものも犠牲と言えます
Or a sacrifice can be
what you give to Jehovah,
ダビデが詩編54編で—
like David said in Psalm 54.
“I will sacrifice to you willingly.”
“わたしは自ら進んで
あなたに犠牲をささげます”
と述べているようにです
And that’s how I view sacrifice.
We’re happy to give of ourselves
to Jehovah God—to serve him.
わたしは犠牲をそのように見ています
And I want to add, too, Sandra has been
エホバ神にお仕えするために
自分自身を喜んで差し出しました
a wonderful partner with me
—willing to go anywhere,
加えて サンドラは
素晴らしいパートナーです
put up with all kinds
of circumstances and difficulties.
A scripture that I—
There are a number
好きな聖句はたくさんありますが—
of good Scriptures,
obviously, that we all love.
特にいつも思いの中にあるのは
ローマ 14:7, 8です
But one in particular
that stays in my mind
is Romans 14:7,8:
“わたしたちは 生きるなら
エホバに対して生き—”
‘We live, we live to Jehovah.
“死ぬならエホバに対して死ぬのです”
‘We die, we die to Jehovah.
“それゆえ 生きるにしても死ぬにしても
わたしたちはエホバのものです”
So whether we live or we die,
we belong to Jehovah.’
そのような決定をしてきました
And we’ve made that decision,
not just because he’s the Creator.
創造者だからというだけではありません
We’ve made the decision
to give ourselves to Jehovah God.
間違いなく考えうる最良の人生を
歩んできました
So, absolutely,
we’ve had the best life possible.
We have no regrets at all
エホバを第一にしてきた人生に
後悔はまったくありません
about what we’ve done with our life,
giving Jehovah the first place.
Bill and Sandra,
it’s been a real privilege
お二人からお聞きできたのは
本当に特権です
to hear more about you, and I know
there are more stories to tell.
60年以上の忠実なエホバへの奉仕ですから
話は尽きないことでしょう
How can you boil down 60-plus years
of loyal service to Jehovah?
貴重な洞察と宝石のような経験を
語ってくださりありがとうございました
But you have given us great insights.
Thank you for sharing those gems with us.
Like the Malenfants, many loyal Witnesses
were not taught the truth
マレンフォント夫妻と同様
多くの証人たちは—
大人になるまで聖書の真理を
教えてもらえませんでした
from the Bible from birth to adulthood.
For some young ones,
seeds of truth are planted along the way
ある若者たちは
真理の種が植えられたものの—
家族の状況ゆえに
何年も芽が出ない状態でした
but can lay dormant
for years due to family circumstances.
Sister Cory Wells explains
how her family’s special talent
コリー・ウェルズ姉妹は
家族の特殊な才能の故に—
命の道になかなか乗り出せなかった
ことを説明しています
almost kept her
from riding on the road to life.
最初にロデオを披露したのは—
The first rodeo I performed in front
of an audience, I was eight years old.
8歳の時です
We were considered
one of the top two acts in rodeo.
わたしたちは一，二を争う
ロデオチームでした
My strength lay in my fearlessness.
私の強みは恐れを
感じないことでした
Even though there was
a certain amount of excitement
まあ 楽しい日々でした
旅行も楽しかったですし—
—it was fun to travel,
to be together as a family—
家族一緒でしたから
でも 虚しかったんです
it was empty.
Trick riding is like gymnastics
on the back of a running horse.
走っている馬の上で
体操するようなものです
We’ve had horses all of our lives.
いつもそばに馬がいました
My father specialized in training horses.
父は馬の調教のプロでした
He used to send us to the mountains,
一日中 山の中で馬に乗ったものです
riding all day long.
And then we’d come home
in the evening,
夕方家に帰ってから
曲乗りを練習しました
and we would start trick riding.
The way we learned was by a book.
本で曲乗りを学びました
We looked at stick pictures
that showed how it should be done,
絵を見ながら やり方を学んだので
試行錯誤の連続でした
and so it was trial and error.
私たちが学ぶと同時に
馬も学んでいきました
At the same time that we were learning,
our horses were learning.
The horse that I rode
just let me do anything.
私がやりたいことを
なんでもさせてくれました
名前はスウィートリップスです
My horse’s name was Sweet Lips.
I was eight when I got him,
and I named him myself.
8歳の時に飼うようになって
自分で名前を付けました
He was like my best friend.
私の親友でした
My parents were very active
in the rodeo as competitors.
両親はロデオ競技に
活発に参加していました
My mom was barrel racing;
母はバレル・レーシング—
my father was
a saddle bronc rider.
父はサドル・ブロンコ・ライダーでした
I grew up as
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
私はエホバの証人として育ちました
but when I was very young,
maybe six or seven,
でも6歳か7歳くらいの時に—
my father stopped
serving Jehovah.
父が真理から
離れてしまいました
To be honest with you,
when they announced that
at the Kingdom Hall,
正直に言うと—
it really didn’t have
much meaning to me at the time.
王国会館で発表があったとき—
どういう意味か分かりませんでした
I didn’t know what it meant.
And I could see people crying,
and so I cried.
みんな泣いていたので—
私も泣きました
But I didn’t really understand it.
でも分かっていませんでした
Really, from that point, our family
was not active as Jehovah’s Witnesses.
このころから家族は
不活発になってしまいました
I grew up on the road,
traveling rodeo to rodeo
旅行しながら大きくなりました
次から次へとロデオを回り—
—from coast to coast
and from the south to the north—
国中をくまなく旅行しました
as far as the roads go.
当初 きょうだいでロデオをしました
The four of us rode initially
コニー ケリー 私 ジムです
—Connie; Kelly; myself;
and my brother, Jim.
家族全員で旅行できていたので
幸せでした
Our family traveled together.
That meant a lot to me.
What separated us
from the others at the time
猛スピードでの技や難しい芸に
あえて挑戦する私たちは—
was the high speed
that we did it at and also
あまりに周りとかけ離れていました
the difficulty with the tricks
that we chose to do.
お客さんはすごく喜びました
People were very excited.
They would hire us back
at the same place year after year.
毎年、同じ会場に呼ばれたものです
Throughout all that time,
こんな生活でしたが—
we did not miss one Memorial.
記念式は一度も欠かしませんでした
心のどこかでそうしなければと
思っていたんです
We were always there.
There was something in us.
We didn’t know it
when we were little,
小さいときは分かっていませんでしたが—
but my parents
had succeeded
in planting
the truth in our hearts.
両親は真理を心に
植え付けてくれていたのです
My link to the truth
was my grandmother.
祖母がわたしと真理との架け橋でした
I can remember going
to the ranch and visiting her.
牧場に住んでいた祖母を訪ねると—
She was very busy, but one thing
that really sticks in my mind
忙しくても 毎日必ず勉強していたのが
印象的でした
is she always studied
—every day.
聖書を読んで
雑誌を深く研究していました
She read her Bible.
Her magazines were studied.
祖母のその姿を見て—
And I think it just put a seed in there
that later on started to grow.
心の中で徐々に真理の種が
育ち始めました
I just felt like
I needed direction.
導きがほしいと思いました
It’s like a line
was drawn in the sand.
砂の上に描いた線のように—
どちらに行くべきか迷っていました
Take one path or the other.
And so, ironically,
the first book
皮肉にも 最初に手に取ったのが—
that I picked up
to read was the Bible.
聖書でした
One of the scriptures
that probably
箴言 3:5，6に感動しました
meant the most to me
was Proverbs 3:5,6:
“心をつくしてエホバに依り頼め”
“Trust in Jehovah
with all your heart
“自分の理解に頼ってはならない”
“and do not lean upon
your own understanding.
“あなたのすべての道において
神を認めよ”
“In all your ways
take notice of him,
and he himself
will make your paths straight.”
“そうすれば神ご自身が—”
“あなたの道筋を
まっすぐにしてくださる”
I used to think
about those words
この言葉通りに生きたいと
強く願ったものです
and what I would have to do
to live up to them.
Although we traveled
with the rodeo
年に10か月はロデオを周っていましたが—
about ten months
out of the year,
地域大会には行きました
we did go
to the district convention,
and the Live Forever book
came out.
「永遠に生きる」の本が
ちょうどいい時に発表されました
And there just came a time
when I knew
変化しなければと
思っている時だったんです
I—I needed to make changes.
A sister started
studying with me,
研究が始まり
自分でも聖書を読み—
and as I started reading
the Bible for myself and studying,
勉強するようになって
エホバが現実の存在になりました
then Jehovah became real.
一人が活発になると—
All it took was one or two people,
and the whole family followed.
家族みんながそれに続きました
My father too returned to the truth.
父も真理に戻ってきました
Trick riding was our family business.
ロデオで私たちの生活は
成り立っていましたが—
It was our livelihood,
but we had decided that we were done.
もう終わりにしようと
家族で決めました
We were going to stop.
それはつまり
これまでのすべてを—
With that decision would come
giving up everything we knew.
手離すということでした
I think—I think the most difficult thing
思い返すと，馬を売る時が
一番つらかったです
for me to do was to sell the horse
—you just, you just get
such a close bond with them
私たちには強い絆があって—
when you’re putting
your life in their hands like that—
いわば一心同体でした
but I was willing to do that.
でも 揺らぎませんでした
I just—
自分で決めた道でしたから
I knew what I wanted to do;
I did it.
85年の10月に
バプテスマを受けました
I got baptized
in October of ʼ85.
最後のロデオは86年の2月で—
Our last performance
was in February of ʼ86.
それで契約がすべて終了しました
We just finished out
our contracts.
86年9月に開拓奉仕をはじめ—
I started pioneering
in September of ʼ86,
それ以来ずっと続けています
and I’ve never stopped.
I also married a man
who loves Jehovah.
エホバを愛する兄弟と結婚しました
We’ve had
the privilege of working
国際建設で夫婦一緒に
奉仕する機会に恵まれました
on international construction projects.
We went to Mexico.
メキシコで働き
ベネズエラでも奉仕しました
We went to Venezuela.
My father is an elder.
My mom is pioneering.
父は長老で—
母は開拓者です
In fact, all of my siblings
have been able
きょうだい全員が—
一度は開拓奉仕を楽しみました
to regular pioneer
at some point in their lives.
We’re presently in the circuit work.
今は巡回奉仕を行なっています
Serving Jehovah together
is such a blessing.
一緒にエホバに仕えるのは
すばらしい祝福です
Everything that we do
every day is for Jehovah.
毎日何をしても—
エホバのためにしているのです
That’s what I wanted to do
これこそが私のしたかったことです
when I made this decision.
If I would have taken
that other path when I was young,
若いときに別の道を歩んでいたら—
今頃は生きていなかったかもしれません
I may not be alive today.
What I did was dangerous.
あれは本当に危険でした
Even fame and fortune in the world
—there’s nothing there.
名声も成功も虚しいだけです
I wanted “the real life.”
真の命を—
エホバに仕えることを望んでいました
I wanted to serve Jehovah.
I have no regrets.
後悔はありません
エホバへの奉仕で—
If I could change anything
こうしておけばよかったと
思うことはありません
when it comes
to my service to Jehovah,
I would change nothing!
もっと仕えたい それだけです
I would just do it better.
It took courage for Cory and her family
to choose loyalty to Jehovah
コリーと家族にとっては
ロデオの仕事よりも—
エホバへの忠節を選ぶには
勇気が求められました
over an exciting rodeo career.
Jehovah will always help us
when we’re prayerfully deciding
好きな活動や仕事が
献身にどう影響するかを—
how an activity or a career we love
祈りのうちに決定するなら
エホバはいつも助けてくださいます
affects our dedication to him.
Can the time it demands,
or even the danger involved,
費やす時間や潜んでいる危険は
魂を込めた奉仕を妨げるでしょうか？
take us away
from whole-souled service?
エホバへの忠節は
人生の重要な決定を下す際—
Our loyalty
to Jehovah is expressed
in how we follow Bible principles
聖書の原則にどのように
従うかによって示せます
when making
any important decision in life.
Few decisions are as important
as whom we choose to marry.
結婚相手として誰を選ぶかは
非常に重要な決定の一つです
Part 1
of our Preparing for Marriage series
“結婚に備える”シリーズのパート１が
2016年5月で紹介されました
appeared in the May 2016 program.
In that dramatization,
そのドラマでは 結婚するには
まだ早すぎることを理解した姉妹が—
a sister realizes she is
too young for a romantic relationship
and that cultivating
Christian qualities now
今クリスチャンの特質を培うなら
将来の結婚に役立つことを悟りました
would help her later
when she’s ready for marriage.
Part 2 in the series next depicts
パート2では交際期間中の二人が—
how a dating couple
can successfully know
どのように“心の中の
秘められた人”を見極め—
“the secret person of the heart”
配偶者とエホバに忠節な結婚相手を
見出せるかを描いています
so that each can find
a marriage mate
who is loyal to them
and to Jehovah.
ジミンとの出会いは
思いがけないものでした
Meeting Ji-min
was completely unexpected.
交際相手を探しては
いませんでしたが—
I wasn’t looking for a girlfriend,
but as we talked,
彼女と話すとすべてが
しっくりきたんです
everything just clicked.
The only problem is the distance.
唯一の問題は距離です
I flew out to see her once,
but most of the time,
飛行機で一度
会いに行きましたが—
ほとんどはオンラインで
コミュニケーションを取るだけです
all we can do
is communicate online.
彼女だ！と
どうすればわかるのだろう？
How can I be sure
she’s the one?
父に相談するのが
最善だと判断しました
I decided the best decision
was to ask my father.
父は 交際が一層真剣に
なっていること—
He knew the relationship
was becoming more serious,
そしてわたしの心配も
理解してくれました
and he appreciated my concerns.
父は言いました
He said:
“The same things are important,
“大切なことは変わらないよ”
“whether the person is next door
“相手が隣に住んでいようと
地球の裏側に住んでいようとね”
“or a world away.
“Most people simply focus on
“見た目や社会的な地位しか
見ない人は多いけれど—”
“appearance or social standing,
“本当に成功するために
必要なものは—”
“but for a truly successful relationship,
“霊性なんだ”
what matters is spirituality.”
Now I had already talked
with Ji-min’s elders,
ジミンの長老たちとも話し—
素晴らしい開拓者だと
言っていました
and they said she was
a wonderful pioneer.
父から
”良かったね”
Dad said: “That’s good,
but it takes more than that.
“でも さらに「心の中の
秘められた人」を知るには—”
It takes time to get to know
‘the secret person of the heart.’”
“時間がかかるんだ”
と言われました
But how do you get to know
でも“心の中の秘められた人”を
知るにはどうすればよいのだろう？
“the secret person of the heart”?
He said: “First, pray.
“まず 祈ること”
“Ask Jehovah
to help you see Ji-min
“ジミンの本当の人となり—”
“as she truly is,
“良い特質も
進歩の必要な特質も—”
“both her good qualities
“両方見れるようエホバに
助けを求めるんだ”
“and ones
that may need improvement.
“そして 彼女に会ったとき
行動を観察すること”
“Also,
when you are able to visit,
“observe her actions.
“友達や両親 会衆の成員に
どのように接しているだろうか？”
“How does she treat her friends,
her parents,
“ones in the congregation?
“それは 将来ジミンがおまえに
どのように接するかを示すものなんだ”
“That’s a good indication of how
she’ll treat you someday.
But it’s not just about her.”
でも彼女の事だけではありません
He had me read Ephesians 5:25:
エフェソス 5:25を読むように
言われました
“夫たちよ 妻を愛し続けなさい”
“Husbands, continue loving your wives,
“キリストが会衆を愛し—”
“just as the Christ
also loved the congregation
“そのためにご自分を引き渡されたのと
同じようにです”
and gave himself up for it.”
He asked,
父は“このような夫になる準備が
できている？”と尋ね—
“Are you ready to be
that kind of husband?”
He thought I was
but that the only person
“できていると思うよ”と
言ってくれました
that truly knows is me.
でも 本当のことを
知っているのは自分だけです
We’ve been able to save up
それから 貯金して
何度も会いに行きました
and make a number
of visits since then,
時間をかけ わたしたち二人の
霊的な人となりを知りました
taking the time to discover
what we both are spiritually.
わたしたちは完璧ではありません
And while we know we’re not perfect,
でも エホバに目を向け続けるなら—
if we keep our focus on Jehovah,
we can be perfect for each other.
互いにとって完璧になれます
Did you notice the ways
they learned more about each other
決定する前に互いをより良く知る方法が
あることがわかりましたか?
before deciding to marry?
Despite the distance,
離れてはいても
霊的な事柄を定期的に話し合い—
they regularly discussed
spiritual matters,
信頼できる大人に付き添ってもらい—
arranged for visits
chaperoned by trusted adults,
訪問したり 集会や宣教に
参加したりするなど—
and worshipped together
at meetings and in the ministry
結婚に備える多くの方法があります
—all good ways
to prepare for marriage.
大都市での証言活動に
参加している夫婦の映像は—
The beautiful scene depicting the couple
in the metropolitan witnessing work
この証言方法がいかに
効果的であるかをよく示しています
is a reminder of how effective
this form of witnessing has become.
We received a report
from San Francisco, California,
米国カリフォルニア州
サンフランシスコからの報告によると—
in the United States,
where publishers have been engaged
in special metropolitan witnessing
伝道者たちは2013年から
大都市での特別な奉仕に参加しています
since 2013.
It’s helping our brothers
reach multiple language groups,
兄弟たちは多くの言語グループを助け
聖書研究を始め 弟子を作っています
start Bible studies,
and make disciples.
When I’m rolling the carts down
to get ready for the work,
カートを引いていると
周りの人々に注目されます
I can feel people’s eyes on me
and it makes me feel proud
移動中でも自分がエホバから
遣わされていることを実感できます
that I’m representing Jehovah
even before I get to the location.
We have a chance
to use our Bibles very regularly.
聖書を何回も開いて
話し合えるんです
心の正直な人たちは聖書の教えを
本当に知りたいと思っています
We talk to honesthearted people
who are interested
in really learning
what the Bible teaches.
Jehovah is reaching people
in those hard-to-reach areas
聖書などについて話し合うことが
難しいところで生活している人にも—
where it could mean their life
エホバは
音信が伝わるようにされます
to even talk about things
such as the Bible.
When you’re part
of the metropolitan work,
大都市での奉仕に
参加すると—
エホバに引き寄せられるよう
人々を助けられます
you get to welcome people
being drawn by Jehovah.
We see thousands of people
every day who walk by our carts.
何千人もの人たちが
毎日カートの前を通るんです
While we’re placing literature
in up to 40 different languages each week,
毎週40もの言語で
配布できますが—
何よりも たくさんの人たちと話せ
多くの研究が取り決められることが—
what’s really exciting is to see
how many conversations we’re starting
and how many Bible studies
we’re initiating.
本当にうれしいです
We’re visible to a lot of people
in the community,
わたしたちは地域社会で
よく知られています
とりわけ 不活発になった
クリスチャンたちにも一目瞭然です
especially those who were inactive
or maybe were raised around the truth.
Jehovah has arranged
to have his people
エホバは世界中から集まる人たちに
会えるよう—
put right in the center
of everything,
わたしたちをあらゆる中心地に
割り当てられます
and we’re able to meet people
from all over the world.
お会いした人たちは—
I’ve met people from Peru, South Africa,
ペルー 南アフリカ 日本
ドイツ 英国
Japan, Germany, England.
France, Italy,
それにフランスやイタリア
カメルーンにコンゴからです
Cameroon, Congo.
Beaucoup!
いっぱい!
In Shona, a greeting
would be something like . . .
ショナ語でのあいさつは
こんな感じです...
. . . , which means
“Would you like to study the Bible?”
今のは日本語での証言です
これは手話の
“聖書を学んでみませんか？”です
. . . , which means “Would you like
to study the Bible?” in sign language.
So when I asked her if she had seen
the sign-language Bible,
手話の聖書を見たことがないと
首を振られたので—
she shook her head no,
and I showed her Acts 17:27.
使徒 17:27をお見せしました
見終わると手話で
“わたしでも分かった！”と喜ばれ—
And as soon as it was done,
she started signing, “I understood that!”
“これが無料のアプリなの？”
と驚かれました
And then she said,
“Didn’t you say this was a free app?”
So, right then,
she started downloading it on her phone.
そして すぐにダウンロードされました
We had a gentleman come up
and wanted to . . .
ある男性に“議論”したい—
First, he said, “debate,”
and then he said, “just discuss.”
いや“ただ話し合い”たいと
近づかれました
But as he was talking with us,
he had to catch his train
本当は電車に乗るつもりの方でしたが—
but he missed three trains
３つも電車をやり過ごし
わたしたちとずっと話してました
because he wanted to continue
the conversation and speak with us.
ただ語り合って わたしたちの
違う面を知ってもらうのも—
It’s a really good experience
because we just get to talk to people
and let them see
a different side of us.
本当に楽しい経験です
It’s not necessarily about whether
we placed a book with him or not.
必ずしも配布する必要はありません
帰り際に“あなたたち夫婦は本当に
素晴らしい大使です”と言われたんです
And in the end, he turned
to my husband and I
and said, “You know, you’re
really good ambassadors.”
We start Bible studies
here every day,
ここで聖書研究が毎日のように始まり
それが世界中に広がっています
and these studies
are conducted globally.
I met Alfredo in 2014,
right before the Memorial.
アルフレードに会ったのは
2014年の記念式前でした
He approached the cart.
カートに近づいてきたんです
He had a rough life.
生活は苦しく 悪いこと
ばかりしていましたので—
He was doing a lot of bad things,
and so he felt
that he couldn’t overcome them.
何も変えられないと
感じていたようです
So I told him that no matter
how big his problems are,
どんなに大きな問題を
抱えていても—
エホバにとって大きすぎる
問題はないことを話し—
they’re not too big
for Jehovah,
and so I encouraged him
to start studying the Bible again.
聖書研究を再開するよう
励ましました
“Come, now,
“さあ 来るがよい”
and let us set matters straight
between us,” says Jehovah.
“わたしたちの間で事を正そう”と
エホバは言われる
“Though your sins are like scarlet,
“たとえあなた方の罪が
緋のようであっても—”
they will be made as white as snow.”
“それはまさに雪のように白くされる”
When Jehovah forgives you,
he forgives you completely.
エホバが人を許してくださる時は
完全にお許しになります
I got baptized,
and in the same month,
わたしはバプテスマを受け
その月から補助開拓奉仕を始めました
I started auxiliary pioneering.
It is such a privilege to be
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の一人でいられることは
本当に特権です
with brothers
all around the world.
世界中に仲間がいるんです
大都市での特別な証言活動にかかる
費用や時間が心配でしょうか？
If anybody is hesitant
to take part
in the special metropolitan
witnessing work,
maybe you’re worried
about finances, time,
それともどうしたらいいのか分からず
慣れてないのでためらいますか？
or you’re just afraid
that it’s something different
and you won’t know
what to do,
そんなに心配しないでください
please don’t let
any of those things stop you.
エホバからの割り当てです
It’s from Jehovah.
Grab hold of it tight,
and don’t let go!
機会を逃さず 手放さないで下さい
Each month,
the brothers and sisters
大都市での証言にサンフランシスコで
参加している兄弟姉妹たちは—
in San Francisco’s
metropolitan witnessing
毎月5000冊以上の
出版物を配布し—
distribute
over 5,000 publications
and start an average
of 185 Bible studies.
平均185件の聖書研究を
取り決めています
After some initial concern
from local authorities
地元当局は金門橋で文書カートを
置くことに 初め懸念しましたが—
over having literature carts
at the Golden Gate Bridge,
今では兄弟たちが聖書の音信を携えて
そこにいることに感謝を述べています
authorities have expressed appreciation
for our brothers being there
with the Bible’s message of hope.
そこでは—
It’s been requested
that we always have on hand
“それでも生きていける 3つの理由”
と題する—
the April 2014 Awake!
with the cover title
2014年4月号の「目ざめよ！」誌を
いつも準備しておくよう依頼されていました
“Why Go On?
—Three Reasons to Keep Living.”
ある時 警官が近づいてきて
こう言いました—
One afternoon an officer
approached a cart and said,
“この雑誌には力がある”
“Well, your magazine worked!”
その警官は橋から飛び降りよう思っていた
若い女性を助けたばかりでした
The police had just helped
a young woman
who was thinking
of jumping from the bridge.
警官たちが近づいたとき彼女は手に
その「目ざめよ！」誌を持っており—
When they reached her,
she had the Awake! issue in her hand
飛び降りないことにしたのです
and had decided not to jump.
この体制下での生活は
誰にとっても困難ですが—
Life in this system
can be difficult for everyone,
わたしたちは証言活動によって
人々を慰め 命の創造者を知って—
but our witnessing work
comforts people
and teaches them to know
and thank their Creator for life.
その方に感謝するよう
助けているのです
And the longer we know Jehovah
as his Witnesses,
エホバを知る期間が
長ければ長いほど—
その忠節な行ないに感謝する理由が
多くなります
the more reasons we find
to thank him for his acts of loyalty.
そして今月の
ミュージックビデオのように—
We’re even moved to sing
our appreciation to Jehovah,
エホバへの感謝を歌いたいと
思うことでしょう
like in this music video entitled
“Our Thanks Go to You.”
タイトルは
“「ありがとう」をあなたへ”
When I cannot find
Any peace of mind,
青い空
探すけど
曇る窓に
You will listen.
My thanks go to you.
陽は射さない
When troubles arise,
Whatever the size,
戻せない
時間〈とき〉想い
うつむく心
For your answers,
Our thanks go to you.
そそぎだす
その手 つかんで
We need not be anxious over anything.
もう迷わない
顔あげて 踏み出せる
You’ll guard our hearts and our thoughts
この足で
If we continue having trust in you to
あなたが いるから
歩きつかれ
Give us peace of mind
When life is unkind.
凍えそうでも
あなたの右手は
For our welfare,
Our thanks go to you.
あたたかい
愛に 包まれ
All the loyal
find you loyal too.
生きてゆける
わたしの“ありがとう”
For your care,
all our thanks go to you.
届きますように
ビデオの中には
経済的な圧力に面している家族や—
We saw the family in our music video
facing economic pressure
and our dear older couple enduring
the stress of failing health.
健康の衰えと向き合っている
年配のご夫婦が登場しました
But as Philippians 4:6 encourages,
フィリピ 4:6には—
they let their “petitions
be made known to God.”
“請願を神に知っていただくように”
とあります
You and I can do the same
for any problem that causes us anxiety.
不安の原因となる
どんな問題に関してもそうできます
We should not only supplicate Jehovah
忍耐できるよう聖霊を
エホバに請願するだけでなく—
to give us his holy spirit
so that we can endure
エホバに感謝をささげ—
but also thank him,
“その忠節な者たちを捨てられない”
ことを確信しましょう
fully assured
that “he will not abandon his loyal ones.”
We’d again like to thank
マレンフォント兄弟姉妹が
出演してくださったことに—
Brother and Sister Malenfant
for being here with us.
重ねて感謝します
With almost 60 years
of full-time service,
ほぼ60年にわたる全時間奉仕で—
the Malenfants have so much
they can share,
マレンフォント兄弟姉妹は
多くの経験をされました
so we’re pleased to announce
それで今月の後半の
JW Broadcastingで—
that an extended version
of their interview
will be released later this month
on JW Broadcasting.
インタビューの続編を
お届けしたいと思います
Finally in our program,
最後に美しい神権的な音楽を
録音するオーケストラの舞台裏を—
we have a special behind-the-scenes visit
with the orchestra
that records
our beautiful theocratic music.
特別にのぞいてみることにしましょう
In December 2015,
2015年12月 16ヵ国から来た
75人の音楽家が—
75 musicians gathered
from 16 countries
for a five-day session at our studio
in Patterson, New York.
ニューヨーク州パタソンにある
スタジオに5日間集結しました
A team of 15 technicians
joined them to record 22 pieces.
15人の技術者と共に
22曲が録音されました
Among several songs
we sing at our meetings
その中には美しく編曲された—
was the stirring arrangement
of song 147,
147番“特別な所有物”があります
“A Special Possession,”
that we sang at this year’s Memorial.
今年の記念式で歌われました
The orchestra took time
from their busy session
オーケストラの皆さんが—
皆さんにクリスチャン愛を送っています
to send you
their Christian love and greetings.
エホバ神を喜んで賛美できる
音楽を備えてくれた—
And we thank them
and the Governing Body
for the music we have
to joyfully praise our God, Jehovah.
オーケストラと統治体に感謝します
We’re happy to have been together
with you for this month’s program.
今月のプログラムを
共に楽しめました
ニューヨーク市ブルックリンから
JW Broadcastingでした
From Brooklyn, New York,
this is JW Broadcasting.